Conglong Li

conglong.li@gmail.com; conglong@google.com conglongli.github.io scholar.google.com/citations?user=nXUS0gYAAAAJ

Research Interests

I'm currently a Senior Research Scientist at Google DeepMind Japan office, working on improving multilingual capabilities of Gemini models. I have a mixed research background between systems and AI, and I worked in many areas including deep learning, similarity search, distributed caching systems, networks, and computer architecture. Regardless of the area, the way I do research is always similar: identify inefficiencies by in-depth analysis, and fix it by algorithm and policy designs.

Education

2014–2020 Ph.D. in Computer Science, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA, USA.

Advisor: David G. Andersen.

Thesis: Learned Adaptive Accuracy-Cost Optimization for Machine Learning Systems.

2013–2014 M.S. in Computer Science, Rice University, Houston, TX, USA.

Advisor: Alan L. Cox.

Thesis: GD-Wheel: A Cost-Aware Replacement Policy for Key-Value Stores.

2009–2013 B.S. in Computer Science, Rice University, Houston, TX, USA.

magna cum laude, distinction in research and creative work.

GPA 4.04, Ranked 1st in Dept. of Computer Science (Class of 2013).

Work Experience

2024–Present Senior Research Scientist, Google DeepMind, Tokyo, Japan.

Working on improving multilingual capabilities of Gemini models.

2021–2024 Senior Researcher, Microsoft, Bellevue/Redmond, WA, USA.

2020–2021 **Researcher**, *Microsoft*, Bellevue, WA, USA.

Member of the DeepSpeed team (github.com/microsoft/DeepSpeed). Worked on improving the communication efficiency via compression, improving computation efficiency via MoE modeling, and improving data efficiency via curriculum learning.

Summer 2019 Research Intern, Microsoft, Bellevue, WA, USA.

Worked on improving approximate nearest neighbor search performance. Designed ML models (GBDT, neural networks) to predict the search termination condition for each query. Achieved up to 7.1 times speedup under the same accuracy targets. Published a paper at SIGMOD 2020.

Summer 2017 Software Engineer Intern, Microsoft, Bellevue, WA, USA.

Worked on designing caching strategies for Bing Ads. Designed ML models (GBDT) to provide intelligent cache refresh decisions. Simulations on production traces demonstrate a potential 35.2 to 106.1 million dollars net profit gain in a quarter. Transferred the project to dev team to ship it in product. Published a paper at WWW 2018.

Summer 2016 Research Intern, Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA.

Worked on designing caching strategies for Bing Ads. Designed domain-specific caching heuristics to save ads scoring cost and improve net profit. Simulations on production traces demonstrate a potential 20.7 to 70.5 million dollars net profit gain in a quarter. Published a paper at SoCC 2017.

Skills

Programming Mostly using Python and C++. Familiar with C, C#, Java.

Publications

arXiv preprint LLM-jp: A Cross-organizational Project for the Research and Development of Fully Open Japanese 2407.03963 LLMs.

Akiko Aizawa, ... **Conglong Li**, ... et al. (80 authors) arXiv preprint arXiv:2407.03963.

Nature Methods OpenFold: Retraining AlphaFold2 yields new insights into its learning mechanisms and capacity 2024 for generalization.

Gustaf Ahdritz, ... **Conglong Li**, ... et al. (34 authors) In *Nature Methods 21, 1514–1524 (2024)*.

AAAI 2024 DeepSpeed Data Efficiency: Improving Deep Learning Model Quality and Training Efficiency via Efficient Data Sampling and Routing.

Conglong Li, Zhewei Yao, Xiaoxia Wu, Minjia Zhang, Connor Holmes, Cheng Li, Yuxiong He. In *38th Annual AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence*.

arXiv preprint DeepSpeed-VisualChat: Multi-Round Multi-Image Interleave Chat via Multi-Modal Causal Atten-2309.14327 tion.

Zhewei Yao, Xiaoxia Wu, **Conglong Li**, Minjia Zhang, Heyang Qin, Olatunji Ruwase, Ammar Ahmad Awan, Samyam Rajbhandari, Yuxiong He. *arXiv preprint arXiv:2309.14327.*

arXiv preprint DeepSpeed-Chat: Easy, Fast and Affordable RLHF Training of ChatGPT-like Models at All 2308.01320 Scales.

Zhewei Yao, Reza Yazdani Aminabadi, Olatunji Ruwase, Samyam Rajbhandari, Xiaoxia Wu, Ammar Ahmad Awan, Jeff Rasley, Minjia Zhang, **Conglong Li**, Connor Holmes, Zhongzhu Zhou, Michael Wyatt, Molly Smith, Lev Kurilenko, Heyang Qin, Masahiro Tanaka, Shuai Che, Shuaiwen Leon Song, Yuxiong He. arXiv preprint arXiv:2308.01320.

NeurIPS 2023 AI for Science Workshop

DeepSpeed4Science Initiative: Enabling Large-Scale Scientific Discovery through Sophisticated Al System Technologies.

Shuaiwen Leon Song, Bonnie Kruft, Minjia Zhang, Conglong Li et al.

In 37th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems AI for Science Workshop.

ICLR 2023 Maximizing Communication Efficiency for Large-scale Training via 0/1 Adam. Yucheng Lu, **Conglong Li**, Minjia Zhang, Christopher De Sa, Yuxiong He. In 11th International Conference on Learning Representations.

arXiv preprint Random-LTD: Random and Layerwise Token Dropping Brings Efficient Training for Large-scale 2211.11586 Transformers.

Zhewei Yao, Xiaoxia Wu, **Conglong Li**, Connor Holmes, Minjia Zhang, Cheng Li, Yuxiong He. arXiv preprint arXiv:2211.11586.

 ${\it ar Xiv preprint } \quad BLOOM: \ A\ 176B-Parameter\ Open-Access\ Multilingual\ Language\ Model.$

2211.05100 Teven Le Scao, ... **Conglong Li**, ... et al. (391 authors). arXiv preprint arXiv:2211.05100.

HiPC 2022 1-bit LAMB: Communication Efficient Large-Scale Large-Batch Training with LAMB's Conver-Best Paper gence Speed.

Conglong Li, Ammar Ahmad Awan, Hanlin Tang, Samyam Rajbhandari, Yuxiong He. In 29th IEEE International Conference on High Performance Computing, Data, and Analytics.

NeurIPS 2022 The Stability-Efficiency Dilemma: Investigating Sequence Length Warmup for Training GPT Models.

Conglong Li, Minjia Zhang, Yuxiong He. In *36th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems*.

- NeurIPS 2022 XTC: Extreme Compression for Pre-trained Transformers Made Simple and Efficient.
 - Oral Paper Xiaoxia Wu, Zhewei Yao, Minjia Zhang, **Conglong Li**, Yuxiong He. In *36th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems*.
- NeurIPS 2022 ZeroQuant: Efficient and Affordable Post-Training Quantization for Large-Scale Transformers. Zhewei Yao, Reza Yazdani Aminabadi, Minjia Zhang, Xiaoxia Wu, **Conglong Li**, Yuxiong He. In *36th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems*.
 - ICML 2022 DeepSpeed-MoE: Advancing Mixture-of-Experts Inference and Training to Power Next-Generation AI Scale.

Samyam Rajbhandari, **Conglong Li**, Zhewei Yao, Minjia Zhang, Reza Yazdani Aminabadi, Ammar Ahmad Awan, Jeff Rasley, Yuxiong He.

In 39th International Conference on Machine Learning.

- ICML 2021 1-bit Adam: Communication Efficient Large-Scale Training with Adam's Convergence Speed.
 Hanlin Tang, Shaoduo Gan, Ammar Ahmad Awan, Samyam Rajbhandari, **Conglong Li**, Xiangru Lian, Ji Liu, Ce Zhang, Yuxiong He.
 In 38th International Conference on Machine Learning.
- SIGMOD 2020 Improving Approximate Nearest Neighbor Search through Learned Adaptive Early Termination.

 Conglong Li, Minjia Zhang, David G. Andersen, Yuxiong He.
 In 2020 ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data.
 - MLSys 2019 Scaling Video Analytics on Constrained Edge Nodes.

 Christopher Canel, Thomas Kim, Giulio Zhou, **Conglong Li**, Hyeontaek Lim, David G. Andersen, Michael Kaminsky, Subramanya R. Dulloor.

 In *Machine Learning and Systems 2019*.
 - WWW 2018 Better Caching in Search Advertising Systems with Rapid Refresh Predictions.

 Conglong Li, David G. Andersen, Qiang Fu, Sameh Elnikety, Yuxiong He.

 In 2018 World Wide Web Conference.
 - SoCC 2017 Workload Analysis and Caching Strategies for Search Advertising Systems.

 Conglong Li, David G. Andersen, Qiang Fu, Sameh Elnikety, Yuxiong He. In 2017 Symposium on Cloud Computing.
 - ANCS 2017 Using Indirect Routing to Recover from Network Traffic Scheduling Estimation Error.

 Conglong Li, Matthew K. Mukerjee, David G. Andersen, Srinivasan Seshan, Michael Kaminsky, George Porter, Alex C. Snoeren.

 In 2017 ACM/IEEE Symposium on Architectures for Networking and Communications Systems.
- CoNEXT 2015 Scheduling Techniques for Hybrid Circuit/Packet Networks.
- Best Paper Nominee He Liu, Matthew K. Mukerjee, **Conglong Li**, Nicolas Feltman, George Papen, Stefan Savage, Srinivasan Seshan, Geoffrey M. Voelker, David G. Andersen, Michael Kaminsky, George Porter, Alex C. Snoeren.

In 11th ACM Conference on Emerging Networking Experiments and Technologies.

EuroSys 2015 GD-Wheel: A Cost-Aware Replacement Policy for Key-Value Stores. **Conglong Li**, Alan L. Cox.

In Tenth European Conference on Computer Systems.

- ACM TACO 2013 Reducing DRAM Row Activations with Eager Read/Write Clustering.
 - Vol. 10(4) Myeongjae Jeon, **Conglong Li**, Alan L. Cox, Scott Rixner. In *ACM Transactions on Architecture and Code Optimization*.

Professional Service

Conferences Reviewer for ICLR 2024, NeurIPS 2023, ICML 2022, MLSys 2020, PACT 2019, Middleware 2018, ICAC 2018, IEEE CLOUD 2018.

Journals Reviewer for Elsevier Neural Networks, ACM Transactions on Storage, ACM SIGMOD Record.